Finding Aid for Computing Center (University of Michigan) records, 1952-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Topical File 1960-1986
  The Computing Center Policy files, 1979-1985, contain documentation on the development of the "Conditions of Use," "Authorization and Charge," and other policies. The Ford Foundation Grant file provides information on a major grant to the College of Engineering, which funded a three year project to teach engineering faculty about digital computing and develop course curricula incorporating use of computing technology. The project was directed by professors Bruce Carnahan and James O. Wilkes.
  MAD files, 1961-1964, include correspondence relating to development of MAD and training material for use of MAD and UMES (University of Michigan Executive System), an early operating system developed for use on the IBM 704 in cooperation with General Motors. The MIDAC file consists of a photocopy of a brochure on the university's first computer, which was developed by the Willow Run Laboratory in 1952.
  The Software Engineering Institute was a proposed collaborative software development laboratory among several Big Ten Universities. The Institute, which ultimately was not established, was in large part a response to the software development needs of the federal government's "Star Wars" program. The files, 1983-1984, offer some insight into the perceived capabilities of programmers and scientists at the Computing Center and the university, and more broadly on the feasibility and reliability of "structured" and "automatic" programming.
  The Supercomputing Files, 1983-1985, are divided into: General, Institute for Computational Studies (ICS), and NSF Supercomputing Sites. The General files include correspondence and reports on the supercomputing needs of the university and proposals for developing such capabilities on campus. The ICS files document the Computing Center's participation in a supercomputing consortium based at the University of Colorado. The NSF Supercomputing Site files document the university's unsuccessful effort to be named host for one of the six National Science Foundation Supercomputing Sites. The records include the UM proposal, comments of the review panel, and material on the NSF site visit.
  Other items of interest include documentation on the Computing Center relationships with the Medical School, College of Literature, Science and Arts, and the Institute for Social Research, an Executive Officers Seminar on the Impact of Computing on Research, a 1985 report on High Speed Computational Facilities at the university, and files on the development of UMNet, the campus computing network.
  - Advisory Task Force on Computing Center Access 1984 (Box 4)
  - Applications Software Support 1978-1984 (Box 4)
  - Business Administration, School of, 1980-83 (Box 4)
  - Center for Information Technology Integration (CITI) undated (Box 4)
  - Center for Machine Intelligence undated (Box 4)
  - Charles Babbage Institute 1979 (Box 4)
  - Commercial Computing Accounts 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - Computer Database Proposal (Box 4)
  - Computer Security 1981 (Box 4)
  - Computing Center
    - Authorization and Charge Policy 1980-1985 (Box 4)
    - Policies
      - 1959-1979 (Box 4)
      - Conditions of Use Policy 1979-1981 (Box 4)
    - Recharge Rates
      - 1960-67 (Box 4)
      - 1977-78 (Box 4)
      - 1981-1983 (Box 4)
    - User Survey 1984 (Box 5)
    - Utilization Reports
      - 1972, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
      - 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - Computing Allocations 1982-1985 (Box 5)
  - Computing Site Proposals 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - CONFER (Advertel) 1985 (Box 5)
  - Conference on "Easier and More Productive Use of Computing Systems" (Ann Arbor) undated (Box 5)
  - Data Concentrator and Computing Center Electronics Shop 1978 (Box 5)
  - Dearborn Campus 1978-1981 (Box 5)
  - Droshan (RPI) Dispute 1981 (Box 5)
  - Educom-Edunet, (Business Plan) 1978 (Box 5)
  - Engineering, College of, (CAEN) 1983 (Box 5)
  - Executive Officers Seminar on Impact of Computing on Research 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Finerman, Aaron (Hiring of) 1978 (Box 5)
  - Flint Campus 1980, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation Grant "Computers In Engineering," 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Galler, Bernard 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - Handicapped Access to Computing Facilities 1982 (Box 5)
  - High-Speed Computational Facilities at UM (report by E. Fronczak) 1985 (Box 5)
  - ILIR Micro 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Information Resource Management 1980 (Box 5)
  - Inter-University Computing Survey 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - ISR (Institute for Social Research) 1981-1984 (Box 5)
  - Learning Technologies Group 1982 (Box 5)
  - Library (Computing Center) 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Lougee, Mike 1984 (Box 5)
  - LS&A (Literature, Science and the Arts) Advisory Committee on Computing, Report 1984 (Box 5)
  - MAC (Multi-Access Computer) Project Controversy 1965 (Box 5)
  - MAD (Michigan Algorithm Decoder)
    - Correspondence, 1961-63 (Box 5)
    - Training Sessions 1961-1964 (for MAD and Michigan Executive System) (Box 5)
  - MAGI (Mathematical Applications Group Inc.), Software License 1981 (Box 5)
  - MDSI (Manufacturing Data Systems Inc.) 1980-1982 (Box 5)
  - Medical School 1979 (Box 5)
  - Microcomputer Education Center, 1984-85 (Box 5)
  - Microcomputer Planning Committee, Ad-Hoc 1983 (Box 5)
  - Microcomputer Sales Policy, 1983-84 (Box 5)
    (Includes text of J. Duderstadt remarks to executive officers re. UM-Apple Contract)
  - Microcomputer Support Group 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - MIDAC (Michigan Digital Automatic Computer) 1952 (Box 5)
    (Photocopy of brochure, original can be found in Bentley Library printed collections, at call no. C477, Engineering Research Institute)
  - Notes From the Director 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - NSF-Sciencenet 1984 (Box 5)
  - Office of Administrative Systems (Box 6)
    - General 1980-1984 (Box 6)
    - Telecommunications Studies 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Personnel 1979-1986, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Phototypesetting 1985 (Box 6)
  - Programming Staff (memos etc.) (Box 6)
  - Publications Policy 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Software Engineering Institute 1983-1984, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Software Surcharge Policy 1983 (Box 6)
  - SPSS Software Support 1981 (Box 6)
    (Includes ICPSR proposal for improved network access to online data)
  - State Fiscal Agency Questionnaire 1979 (Box 6)
  - Statistics Research Lab 1983 (Box 6)
  - Student Misuse of Computing Resources 1968-1977 (Box 6)
  - Sub-committee on Centers and Institutes (re Computing Center's administrative reporting relationship) 1983 (Box 6)
  - Supercomputing
    - General 1983-1984 (Box 6)
    - Institute for Computational Studies (ICS) at CSU 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - NSF Supercomputing Sites 1984
      - UM Proposal 1984 (Box 6)
      - NSF Site Visit, 1984, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Reviews of UM Proposal 1984 (Box 6)
  - Task Force for Technology on Teaching and Learning 1983 (Box 6)
  - TAXIR (software package) 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Technology Based Industry Committee 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Technology Transfer Steering Committee 1980 (Box 6)
  - Telecommunications Planning 1983 (Box 7)
  - Telecommunications Final Planning Report 1984 (Box 7)
  - Telecommunications Needs Assessment 1984 (Box 7)
  - Telenet (Box 7)
  - Telephones/Teletypes/Data Sets 1966-1970 (Box 7)
  - Twentieth Anniversary Observance 1979 (Box 7)
  - UM-Net
    - 1979-1981 (Box 7)
    - 1982 (Box 7)
    - 1983 (Box 7)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - University Hospital, Telecommunications and Information Systems Planning 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - University Library 1984-1986 (Box 7)
  - UNIX 1982-1985 (Box 7)
  - User Services Project Report 1985 (Box 7)
  - Voice Message System 1983 (Box 7)
- MTS (Michigan Terminal System) 1970-1986
  The MTS (Michigan Terminal System) series (1 linear ft., 1970-1986) provides documentation on the development and marketing of the MTS operating system developed by the Computing Center. For the most part the files are administrative rather than technical. The General files include several reports on MTS development and current features. The Licensing and the Marketing Plans files provide some indication of the range of clients who purchased or considered purchasing MTS. The Workshops subseries provides some information on the implementation of MTS code and features. The workshops were held annually for administrators and programming staff of the six MTS Group universities. The files for individual workshops vary from little more than schedules, to reports on individual sessions, to complete transcripts.
  - General (Box 7)
    (Includes two reports, 1970 and 1980 on MTS development and describing current features and usage)
  - Development and Installation (Joint Statement of the MTS Installations Managers) June, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Directors Meeting 1984 (Box 7)
  - Installation Managers, Correspondence 1979-1986, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Licensing
    - Correspondence re. policy development 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Licensing Inquiries and Proposals 1977-1986 (Box 7)
    - Marketing Opinion Research (MOR) 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - Marketing Plans 1985-1986 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1979-1981 (Box 7)
  - MTS Public Files, Staff responsible for 1982, 1984 (Box 7)
  - MTS:Forum Charges 1984 (Box 7)
  - Public Files-Staff Responsibilities 1982-1984 (Box 7)
  - Text Processing Task Force, Final Report 1980 (Box 7)
  - Wayne State, 1982-83 (Box 7)
  - Workshops
    - 1976 (Box 7)
    - 1979 (Box 7)
    - 1980-1985 (Box 8)
- Word Processing Project (UM & IBM) 1978-1983
  The Word Processing Project series (.25 linear ft., 1978-1983) documents a project headed by Bernard Galler to investigate the possibilities for text processing on computers. Portions of the project were conducted jointly with IBM. The files, which consist primarily of correspondence and reports, illustrate some of the early thinking on the development of word processing capabilities on mainframe systems and personal computers.
  - Project Proposal 1982, 2 folders
    - Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports 1978-1983, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Conference on Word Processing 1980 (Box 8)
- Vendors
  The Vendors series (1.75 linear ft., 1958-1984) provides information on the purchase, installation and operation of computing equipment and the Computing Center's relations with computer companies. There are substantial records for each of the major vendors: Apple, Amdahl, Apollo, Burroughs, and IBM.
  The IBM and Amdahl subseries are the most significant. They include separate files for each of the major machines or systems installed by the Computing Center. The files for a machine may include information on its purchase, various reports and statistics on usage, and material relating to its discontinuance and resale. The IBM material also includes files on the Time Sharing System (TSS) development. IBM began developing TSS for use on its 360/67 machine. The Computing Center was a partner in some phases of TSS development. When IBM's development efforts proved slower than expected, Computing Center staff continued development work on a time shared operating system that became MTS. Significant files include the Code Transfer Agreement between UM and IBM and several reports comparing TSS, MTS and other time sharing systems.
  The Amdahl records document the Computing Center's conversion to Amdahl mainframes in the mid 1970s. Files include a transcript of the Regents' meeting at which the Computing Center argued for the purchase of the Amdahl 470/V6 machine over a Burroughs computer. The Burroughs files also include information on this purchase.
  - Apple 1983 (Box 8)
  - Apollo 1982 (Box 8)
  - Amdahl
    - Computers and Equipment
      - 470V/6
        - Correspondence 1973-1979 (Box 8)
          (Includes information on purchase and replacement of 470V/6)
        - Regent's Proceedings (transcript of meeting at which Burroughs Corp. presented case against CC purchases of Amdahl 470V/6) (Box 8)
        - Documentation (brochures, manuals, and technical information) 1974-1979 (Box 8)
      - 470V/7 1980-1985 (Box 9)
      - 470V/8 1981-1984 (Box 9)
      - 5860, 1982-1984 (Box 9)
      - 1200, 1984 (Box 9)
  - AT&T 1984 (Box 9)
  - Burroughs 1975 (Box 9)
    (information on Burroughs attempt to sell UM a model B7700 computer. See also the Regents Proceedings transcript under Amdahl 470/V6.)
  - IBM
    - General, 1981-198 (Box 9)
      (Includes material from site visit by IBM officials)
  - IBM (cont.)
    - Computers and Equipment
      - Inventories of Equipment
        - 1959-1974, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Model 650 1956-1957 (Box 9)
      - Model 704 and 709 1959-1962 (Box 9)
      - Model 704, Plans for Installation 1958-1959 (Box 9)
      - System 709, Purchase of 1960 (Box 9)
      - System 360 1965-1966 (Box 9)
      - System 360/20 1967-1976 (Box 9)
      - System 360/50 1965-1966 (Box 9)
      - System 360 System 1965-1966 (Box 9)
      - System 360/67
        - Comment on Purchase of 1969 (Box 9)
        - Triplex model 1972 (Box 9)
        - Maintenance and Storage Devices 1966-1975 (Box 9)
        - Sale of 1975 (Box 9)
      - System 360/70 (Box 9)
      - System 360/85 (Box 9)
      - System 370/168 1972-1974 (Box 9)
      - Model 1130 1968-1971 (Box 9)
      - Model 1401 1962-1965 (Box 9)
      - Model 3090/400 1986 (Box 9)
      - Model 7090 1960-1966
        - Usage Statistics 1962-1965 (Box 9)
      - Disk Pack Storage Devices 1967-1973 (Box 9)
      - Remote Terminals and Storage Devices 1969-1978 (Box 9)
      - 3270 Display Station, 1972 (Box 9)
    - Time Sharing System Development
      - Code Transfer Agreement, IBM-UM 1967 (Box 9)
      - Cost and Machine Considerations 1970 (Box 9)
      - Expansion of Use for Time Shared Systems (memos, proposals for educational applications of TSS) 1964-1966 (Box 9)
      - Extended Arithmetic Functions on IBM 360/67 1965-1970 (Box 9)
      - Joint Study Proposal 1970 (Box 9)
      - MTS-TSS Comparisons 1967-1969 (Box 9)
      - Reports on Time Sharing Systems-including MTS 1965-1965 (Box 9)
      - Segment Relocation Hardware for IBM 360 (papers and notes), 1965-66 (Box 9)
    - UM-IBM Projects (Box 10)
      - Audio Distribution System 1983 (Box 10)
      - Freshman Composition Proposal 1984 (Box 10)
  - Service Bureau Corp. 1962 (Box 10)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of a single folder of undated photographs, mainly of the IBM 7090 machine in the North University Building. There are also a few snapshots of Computing Center personnel.
  - IBM Model 7090 at NUB and misc. snapshots (Box 10)
- Administrative Records 1959-1992
  The Administrative Records series (6 linear ft., 1959-1992) is arranged into the following subseries: Budget Material, Committees, Correspondence, Organization and Planning, Personnel, Proposals, Papers and Lecture Notes, Reports, Research Systems, Space Planning, and Computer Files.
  - Budget Material 1959-1993
    Budget materials document the Computing Center's financial status for several years that are missing in the earlier accession and continue a run into the early 1990s. The subseries also contains MTS (Michigan Terminal System) utilization records and computer allocations by university units, each of which were influential in justifying and supporting budget requests.
    - 1959-1972, 13 folders (Box 10)
    - 1987-1990, 2 folders; 3 folders (Box 10)
    - 1991-1993, 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Allocations 1968-1971, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Utilization 1960-1988, 13 folders (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Income History 1981-1990 (Box 11)
      - IBM (International Business Machines) Rentals 1966-1967 (Box 11)
      - Projections 1972-1977 (Box 11)
      - Purchase of 360/67 1969 (Box 11)
  - Committees
    Committee files reflect the collaborative and interdisciplinary nature of University of Michigan computing and technological planning, particularly in the records of ITPC (Information Technology Policy Committee) and ITAC (Information Technology Architecture Committee). ITPC, a ten member advisory panel was formed in 1987 as a reconstituted Computing Policy Committee (CPC), with a tightened focus for advising on major functions: strategic direction, priority setting and policy recommendation. ITAC initiated that same year, was charged with developing the design for and recommending implementation tactics for a university-wide, comprehensive information technology architecture. Documents containing valuable background information on issues scheduled for deliberation often supplement committee files, which are mainly comprised of minutes, agendas, and correspondence.
    - A (Committee A) 1986-1987 (Box 12)
    - Advanced TV Production Committee 1989 (Box 12)
    - Biblical Studies and the Computer Committee undated (Box 12)
    - Committee on Computer Policy (CPC) 1983 (Box 12)
    - Curriculum Committee 1981-1983 (Box 12)
    - Directors Committee 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC) Formative 1986-1987 (Box 12)
    - ITAC 1987-1988 (Box 12)
    - Information Technology Policy Committee (ITPC) 1988, 2 folders (Box 12)
      (Includes July 1988 retreat)
    - ITPC Retreat 1990 (Box 12)
    - Manager's Committee 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Micro-computing Planning Committee 1983 (Box 12)
    - Mid-Manager's Committee 1989-1990 (Box 12)
    - Planning Advisory Group (PAG) Topical Task Force 1990 (Box 12)
    - Policy Committee 1986-1987 (Box 12)
    - Research Systems Executive Committee 1990-1992, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Resource Administration / Research Systems Task Force 1991 (Box 12)
    - Scientific Computation Committee 1988 (Box 12)
    - Selection Committee (Hardware and Software) 1989-1990 (Box 12)
    - Task Group on Combined Operations,1986 (Box 12)
    - University Computing Advisory Committee 1988 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence (Includes e-mail printouts)
    - General 1961-1991, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Control Data 1963-1967 (Box 13)
    - Controlled Data vs IBM 1963-1967, 1972 (Box 13)
    - IBM 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - Intersystems 1987 (Box 13)
    - Ralphnet Digest (moderated listserv) 1990-1991 (Box 13)
  - Organization and Planning
    The Organization and Planning subseries is important for documenting internal studies, reorganizations and methodologies for long-term planning. "Topical Task Force Reports," for example, summarize in 1990 statistics support, scientific computation, applications in use, electronic mail, the evolution of MTS (Michigan Terminal System), the university library's online bibliographic system (MIRLYN), staff morale, and staff training and development.
    - General 1979-1990, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Consulting and Support Services 1989-1992 (Box 13)
    - Distributed Computing 1991 (Box 13)
    - Planning Model Task Force 1991 (Box 13)
    - Proposed Expansion of the Computing Center Facility 1975 (Box 13)
    - Reorganization Implementation Review Committee 1989 (Box 13)
    - Reorganization 1991 (Box 13)
    - Research Systems, Group 2 1990 (Box 13)
    - Retreat 1991 (Box 13)
    - Topical Task Force Reports 1990 (Box 13)
  - Personnel
    - Associate Director 1987 (Box 13)
    - Development Officer 1987 (Box 13)
    - General 1976-1991, 4 folders (Box 43)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2021 ]
    - Institutional File System (IFS) 1988 (Box 13)
    - Management Development 1987-1988 (Box 13)
    - Manager Workshop 1988 (Box 13)
    - Office Position Study 1981 (Box 13)
    - Research Scientist 1987-1988 (Box 13)
    - Research Scientist Award 1988-1991 (Box 13)
    - Research Systems Associate Director Search 1990, 1 folders (Box 43)
    - Salary Program 1991 (Box 13)
    - Salary Study 1972 (Box 13)
  - Proposals
    Proposals and Reports are each a rich source in this series for data documenting the Computing Center's proactive culture and energy for adaptation to changing technology. Proposals provide information on the germination of ideas, technical requirements, and clearly synthesized background for projects envisioned and both realized and unrealized. Reports (mostly unpublished) include detailed documentation for systems and software and thorough technical descriptions for special projects. Researchers should note that the Computing Center published a large number of significant technical reports. They are part of the University of Michigan Computing Center Publications record group.
    - "ConComp" (Research in Conversational Use of Computers) 1965 (Box 13)
    - "Digital Computing System for University of Michigan RFP," 1968 (Box 13)
    - "Development of a General Purpose Operating system for Handling Large Data Bases," 1972 (Box 13)
    - "Ethernet Support," 1989 (Box 13)
    - "High Speed Internet," 1988 (Box 13)
    - "Information Technology in Higher Education: Values and Ethics," 1989 (Box 13)
    - "Proposal for University of Michigan Computer Network," 1981 (Box 13)
    - "Proposal for Expanded Micro-computer Support," 1983 (Box 13)
    - "Program to Expand Computing Center," 1965 (Box 13)
    - "Proposal to the National Science Foundation for a Gateway between the Merit Computer Network and the Internet," 1989 (Box 14)
    - "Sample Set of Research Projects Utilizing the Computer," and "Supplement to A Program to Expand the University of Michigan's Computing Center," 1966 (Box 14)
    - "Segment Relocation Hardware Proposal and Associated Software for IBM System/360," 1965 (Box 14)
    - "Study of File Management in Virtual Storage Environments," 1975 (Box 14)
    - General 1970, 1991 (Box 14)
    - "Masters' and Doctors' Theses in Computer Science," 1972 (Box 14)
    - "Readings for Math/CCS 473," 1970-71 (Box 14)
  - Reports
    - General 1957-1992, 3 folders (Box 14)
      (Includes "Technical Subcommittee Report on Hierarchical Computing at the University of Michigan," 1979; "The Computer and Its Current Role in Architectural Education;" 1967; "Computing Center, Status," 1976-1977, by R.C. F. Bartels, 1977)
    - "Algorithm for Equivalence Declarations," 1972 (Box 14)
    - "Applicability of Hash Coding Techniques in Time-Shared Data Handling," 1968 (Box 14)
    - "Architecture of Compilers," 1964 (Box 14)
    - "Computing Center Organization, System Architecture and Hardware Facilities," 1985 (Box 14)
    - "Display File (DF) Routines User's Guide," 1970 (Box 14)
    - "Documentation for MIDAS," 1976 (Box 14)
    - "Educational Computing at the University of Michigan: A Survey of Activities and Resources," 1973-74 (Box 14)
    - "Elementary Statistics Using MIDAS," 1976 (Box 14)
    - "Engineering Design Report," 1967 (Box 14)
    - "Engineering Design Report Modified 338 Display Interface," 1967 (Box 14)
    - "Hierarchical Descriptions, Universal Spaces and Adaptive Systems," 1968 (Box 14)
    - "Industrial Hygiene Report," 1981 (Box 14)
    - "JRP Statistical Programs for High Speed IBM Digital Computers," 1971 (Box 14)
    - "Multi-Programming in Small Systems Environment," 1969 (Box 14)
    - "Office of Science and Technology," 1987 (Box 14)
    - "P.O. Memo 71: Part 1 of preliminary manual describing the physical characteristics and functions of the D17Airborn digital computer," undated (Box 14)
    - "Preliminary Maintenance Manual of the Minuteman D17A Computer and Associated Test Equipment," 1960 (Box 15)
    - "Priority Services Review," 1991 (Box 15)
    - "PROCRU-Program for PROMAX, PROOCRSTES and Other Direct Factor Rotations," 1968 (Box 15)
    - "Program and Addressing Structure in a Time-Sharing Environment," undated (Box 15)
    - "Programming Manual for MITILAC 659 Routine for Use at the University of Michigan," 1956 (Box 15)
    - "Raws II: A Multiple Regression Analysis Program," 1963 (Box 15)
    - "Real Time Computing," 1965 (Box 15)